从
YTS.MX 下载
Downloaded from
YTS.MX
YIFY 电影官方网站：
Official YIFY movies site:
YTS.MX
&lt;i>埃尔西诺高速公路交通陷入停滞。&lt;/i>
Traffic is at a standstill
on the Elsinore motorway.
&lt;i>紧急车辆已出动。
请让他们过去。&lt;/i>
Emergency vehicles have been dispatched.
Please let them through.
&lt;i>我们还不知道原因。&lt;/i>
We don't know the cause yet.
对伊丽莎白来说，“爱你的邻居”
不只是一句话。
To Elisabeth, "love thy neighbour"
was not just a phrase.
这是一种处世之道。
It was a way of being in the world.
一种当牧师的方式。
一种当妻子和母亲的方式。
A way to be a pastor.
And a way to be a wife and a mother.
你对她来说意味着一切。
You meant everything to her.
抱歉。请让我来做。
Sorry. Please let me do it.
现在有什么事吗？
比如咖啡？
Will there be something now?
Like coffee?
你好，Regitze。
我们能一起做这件事真是太好了。
Hello, Regitze.
Great that we could do this together.
牧师住宅是官方住所。
新牧师很不耐烦。
Parsonages are official residences.
The new pastor is impatient.
我试过几次给 Jan 打电话，
但我不确定他是否开始收拾行李了。
I've tried to call Jan several times,
but I'm not sure he started packing.
他没有认真对待这件事。
He's not taking this seriously.
牧师住宅是正式的住所。
新牧师必须搬进来。
A parsonage is an official residence.
The new pastor has to move in.
简，我们理解你的悲伤，
你的震惊，但生活还得继续。
Jan, we understand your grief,
your shock, but life must go on.
生活还有很多事情要做。
Life still has a lot to give.
我有一本小书给你，
&lt;i>掌握悲伤&lt;/i>。
I have a little book for you,
Mastering Grief.
- 简……
- 胡说八道。
- Jan...
- What nonsense.
愚蠢的混蛋！
Stupid wanker!
爸爸！
Dad!
快……快出来。
海涅现在已经离开了。
Just... just come out.
Heine has left now.
太好了。
Great.
那么，我去煮点咖啡。
So, I'll make some coffee.
我们需要打开一些东西。
There is something we need to open.
我的竖琴变成了哀悼，
我的笛子变成了哭泣者的声音。
My harp is turned to mourning and
my flute to the sound of those who weep.
我们必须打开它。我们两个。
现在她已经不在了。
We have to open this. The two of us.
Now that she is no longer here.
这就是我被告知的。
That's what I was told.
&lt;i>亲爱的你们。&lt;/i>
Dear you.
&lt;i>我最亲爱的你们两个。&lt;/i>
My dearest you two.
&lt;i>我站在天堂之门前。&lt;/i>
I stand before the pearly gates.
&lt;i>其实我在床上，
但你们知道我的意思。&lt;/i>
I'm in my bed, actually,
but you know what I mean.
&lt;i>我很平静。我的信仰与我同在。
我唯一的悲伤和担忧就是你。&lt;/i>
I'm calm. My faith is with me.
My only sorrow and worry is you.
&lt;i>当你是一个家庭时，
尤其是像我们这么小的家庭 - &lt;/i>
When you are a family,
especially one as small as ours -
&lt;i>你们必须努力工作
才能互相支持 - &lt;/i>
you must work hard
to be there for each other -
&lt;i>无论存在什么差异
和分歧。&lt;/i>
regardless of differences
and disagreements.
&lt;i>Regitze，Jan 是你的父亲。记仇或断绝关系是没有用的。&lt;/i>
Regitze, Jan is your father. It's no use
holding a grudge or cutting him off.
&lt;i>他是你唯一的父亲。&lt;/i>
He's the only father you've got.
&lt;i>简，她是你唯一的女儿。
振作起来。&lt;/i>
Jan, she's your only daughter.
Pull yourself together.
&lt;i>即使你不得不放下你的骄傲。&lt;/i>
Even if you have to swallow your pride.
&lt;i>有时你必须走很远才能和对方达成共识。&lt;/i>
Sometimes you have to go a long way
to meet each other halfway.
&lt;i>Regitze，你父亲和我谈到了步行卡米诺 - &lt;/i>
Regitze, your father and I talked
about walking the Camino -
&lt;i>从阿斯托加到孔波斯特拉大教堂。&lt;/i>
from Astorga to the cathedral
in Compostela.
&lt;i>这是我一生的梦想。
我做不到。&lt;/i>
It was a lifelong dream of mine.
I won't make it.
&lt;i>所以这是我最后的愿望：
希望你们俩能一起走上卡米诺之路。&lt;/i>
So this is my final wish:
that you two walk the Camino together.
&lt;i>我相信这对你们有好处。&lt;/i>
I believe it will do you good.
&lt;i>照顾好自己，照顾好彼此。&lt;/i>
Take care of yourselves, and each other.
- 卡米诺之路？
- 是的，卡米诺之路。
- The Camino?
- Yes, the Camino.
- 260 公里。
- 好的。
- 260 kilometers.
- Okay.
需要 11 天。
It'll take 11 days.
11 天？
11 days?
也许有更短的路线？
周末？
Maybe there's a shorter route?
Over a weekend?
你一点都不想念她吗？
Don't you miss her at all?
我想念她吗？
她是我的母亲，我当然想念她。
Do I miss her?
She is my mother, of course I miss her.
那么也许你会考虑
尊重她的遗愿。
Then perhaps you'll consider
respecting her last wish.
你们俩打算做什么？
What are you two going to do?
我真的不知道。你知道情况是怎样的。
I don't really know. You know how it is.
如果你们继续徒步旅行，你们俩终于可以交谈了。
You two could finally talk,
if you go on that hike.
对。
Right.
- 她埋在哪里？
- 公墓。
- Where's she buried?
- Common grave.
嘿！
Hey!
- 不要把花扔在那里。
- 我妈妈的骨灰盒刚刚放在这里。
- Don't dump your flowers there.
- My mom's urn was just put down here.
那只是一片草坪。公墓
在那边的桦树林旁边。
That's just a lawn. The common grave
is over there by the birch grove.
好的。给你。
Okay. Here you go.
- 和他一起旅行会很漫长。
- 你的情况怎么样？
- It's going to be a long trip with him.
- How about your situation?
- 你和那个荷兰人谈过吗？
- 你觉得这太热了吗？
- Have you talked with the Dutch guy?
- Do you think this is too warm?
我明白
这可能会让人不知所措。
I understand
that it can be overwhelming.
- 但你和他谈过吗？
- 我还没来得及。
- But have you talked to him?
- I haven't gotten around to it.
又是我爸爸吗？
Is it my father again?
现在是关于背包里的一块石头的事情。
Now it's something about a stone
in the backpack.
一开始他从不发短信。
现在他一直发短信。
First he never texts.
Now it never stops.
现在是关于石头的事情？
And now something about a stone?
我想你妈妈现在见到我们会很高兴。
I think it would really
please your mother to see us now.
那里的美食很棒。
It's a great cuisine down there.
我期待着
品尝 caldeirada。
I'm looking forward
to tasting caldeirada.
- 这次旅行不是为了吃。
- 对。
- This trip is not about eating.
- Right.
- 那是什么？
- 你的 Camino Pass。
- What's that?
- Your Camino Pass.
- 我是 Joaquín。你叫什么名字？
- 我叫 Jan。
- I'm Joaquín. What's your name?
- My name is Jan.
- 欢迎，Jan。这是你的第一次 Camino 之旅？
- 是的。
- Welcome, Jan. Your first Camino?
- Yes, it is.
- 太棒了。&lt;i>Buen Camino！&lt;/i>
- 谢谢。
- Wonderful. Buen Camino!
- Thank you.
请告诉我。我是 Joaquín。
Please. I'm Joaquín.
- 请问您的名字？
- Regitze。
- Your name, please?
- Regitze.
很高兴认识您。
这是您第一次走 Camino 吗？
Nice to meet you.
It's your first time Camino?
是的，我母亲刚刚死于癌症，
这是她的最后愿望。
Yeah, my mother just died of cancer,
and this was her last wish.
太好了。&lt;i>Buen Camino！&lt;/i>
Great. Buen Camino!
- 好了。
- “第一步。”
- There we go.
- "The first step."
这是我和你母亲开始新事物时使用的表达方式。
That's an expression your mother and I
used when starting something new.
- 我以前从未听说过。
- 好吧，我们听说过。我们说过。
- I've never heard that before.
- Well, we did. We said that.
好的，没问题。
Okay, fine.
- 第一步。
- 是的，第一步。
- The first step.
- The first step, yes.
第一天
还有 260 公里
DAY 1
260 kilometers to go
谷歌说我们走得太远了！
Google says we've gone too far!
第一张地图是在公元前 4,000 年在粘土上绘制的。它们仍然有效。
The first maps were drawn on clay
in 4,000 BC. They still work.
看，我们必须回去
然后右转。
Look, we have to go back there
and then right.
看，我们走得太远了。
我们必须回去然后右转。
Look, we walked too far.
We have to go back and then right.
&lt;i>Buen Camino！&lt;/i>
Buen Camino!
- 有些人打车出城。
- 我们也可以这样做吗？
- Some people take a taxi out of town.
- We could do that too?
想想看，自中世纪以来，朝圣者就一直来到这里。
To think that pilgrims have walked
here since the Middle Ages.
1200 年的传统！
A 1200-year-old tradition!
真的很神奇。
Really magical.
- 你没带很多东西？
- 我们在西班牙。
- You haven't brought a lot?
- We're in Spain.
天气晴朗温暖。
It's sunny and warm.
穿着网球鞋走260公里？
260 kilometers in those tennis shoes?
我觉得你不明白
这次徒步到底是为了什么。
I don't think you understand
what this walk is all about.
朝圣之路启迪并提升了朝圣者。别管穿什么鞋了。
The Camino enlightens and elevates
its pilgrims. Screw the footwear.
如果你的母亲在这里，她会唱“赞美上帝创造的一切”。
If your mother was here, she'd sing
"Praise All Things That God Has Made".
- 她的声音真好听。
- 你会让她安静下来。
- She had such a fine voice.
- You would have asked her to be quiet.
你为什么这么说？
Why do you say that?
因为每当她唱歌时你总是会这样。
Because you always did
whenever she sang.
我没有！我们经常一起唱歌。
I did not! We often sang together.
&lt;i>Buen Camino！&lt;/i>
Buen Camino!
&lt;i>- Buen Camino。&lt;/i>
- 你好。
- Buen Camino.
- Hello.
他哭了吗？
Did he cry?
没关系，爸爸。我们只是记得不同而已。
It's okay, Dad.
We just remember things differently.
你们俩独处的时候
可能还唱过歌。
You probably sang
when you two were alone.
我不知道。
I wouldn't know about that.
&lt;i>Buen Camino。&lt;/i>
Buen Camino.
嗯……我们还有
16 公里要走，对吧？
Well... we still have
16 kilometers to go, right?
你需要休息一下吗？
Do you need a break?
哦不！它们需要被挤破。
Oh no! They need to be popped.
&lt;i>- Buen Camino！&lt;/i> 水泡？
- 是的，很大的水泡。
- Buen Camino! Blisters?
- Yeah, big ones.
- 我觉得你穿的鞋不对。
- 哦，你这么认为吗？
- I think you're wearing the wrong shoes.
- Oh, you think so?
是的，我认为你一定在那些东西上戳了个洞。
Yeah, and I think you must poke
a hole in those.
- 是的，我刚告诉他。
- 我有这个。
- Yeah, I just told him.
- I have this one.
- 我可以自己做。
- 不，不，不！没关系。
- I can do it myself.
- No, no, no! It's okay.
- 等等。
- 太好了，你什么都有！
- Hold on.
- Nice you have everything!
好的...
Okay...
好些了吗？
Better?
- 谢谢！
- 我是 Mirna。我来自克罗地亚。
- Thank you!
- I'm Mirna. I'm from Croatia.
我是 Jan，
我是来自丹麦的 Regitze。
This is Jan,
and I'm Regitze from Denmark.
&lt;i>Buen Camino！&lt;/i> 再见。
Buen Camino! See you.
- 她人真好。
- 她真是烦人。
- How nice of her.
- She was bloody annoying.
- 你完成了吗？
- 是啊，是啊！
- Are you done yet?
- Yeah, yeah!
- 快点。
- 嘿！
- Hurry up.
- Hey!
- 挪威。
- 丹麦。
- Norway.
- Denmark.
- 我来自奥斯陆。
- 哥本哈根。嗨。
- I'm from Oslo.
- Copenhagen. Hi.
- 你一个人走朝圣之路？
- 我跟我爸爸一起走。是的。
- You're walking the Camino alone?
- I'm walking with my dad. Yeah.
我本来应该跟
我的女朋友一起走的，但结果没成。
I was supposed to walk with
my girlfriend, but it didn't turn out.
Okay, sure.
- 对。
- 不是那样的。
- Right.
- Didn't work that way.
我们谈到了买房、买电动车、一起生孩子。
We talked about buying a house,
an electric car, having a child together.
哦，哇。
Oh, wow.
是的。
Yeah.
然后她爱上了
她的健身教练。
Then she fell in love
with her fitness trainer.
哦，该死。
Oh, shit.
她的巴西教练
从头到脚都纹身。
Her Brazilian trainer
tattooed from head to toe.
- 对不起。
- 没关系。
- I'm sorry.
- It's fine.
只是……
It's just...
- 纹身、健身、巴西。
- 太多了。
- Tattoos, fitness, Brazil.
- It's a lot.
好吧，也许最好
想点别的。
Well, it's probably good
to think about something else.
- 你的头发颜色和 Liv 一样。
- 哦，真有趣。
- You have the same hair color as Liv.
- Oh, that's funny.
- 给我拿点卫生纸！
- 是的。抱歉。
- Bring me some toilet paper!
- Yeah. Sorry.
- 嘿，哥本哈根！
- 嘿，奥斯陆。
- Hey, Copenhagen!
- Hey, Oslo.
我会帮我们办理登机手续。
I'll check us in.
你好！我刚才在想
你父亲和他的脚。
Hello again! I was just thinking
of your father and his feet.
- 真的吗？太好了。
- 把这些带给你父亲。
- Oh, really? That's nice.
- Take these to your father.
我是个脚很大的女人，
可以调整它们以适合他。
I'm a woman with big feet,
and they can be adjusted to fit him.
- 不，我们不能带走它们。
- 是的，谢谢。我有靴子。
- No, we can't take them.
- Yes, please. I have my boots.
- 真的吗？
- 一切都好！
- Really?
- All good!
- 非常感谢！
- 是的。
- Thank you so much!
- Yes.
- 再见！
- 谢谢！
- Bye!
- Thank you!
- 我们有房间了。
- 太棒了！你看。
- We've got a room.
- Great! And look.
Mirna 给了你她的凉鞋。
它们很完美。
Mirna gave you her sandals.
They're perfect.
你妈妈讨厌男人
穿袜子穿凉鞋。
Your mother hated men
with socks in sandals.
嗯，她现在不在这里。
Well, she's not here now.
就拿去吧。
Just take them.
“谢谢，Mirna。谢谢，Gitze。
不用客气，爸爸。”
"Thanks, Mirna. Thanks, Gitze.
You're welcome, Dad."
- 嗨。
- Hi.
好吧，我们聊了一会儿，但是……
Well, we're talking a little, but...
&lt;i>关于什么？
你在说些什么真实的事情吗？&lt;/i>
About anything?
Are you talking about anything real?
我真的在努力。
I'm really trying.
我不知道我是否想告诉他
我要当妈妈了。
I don't know if I want to tell him
I'm going to be a mother.
&lt;i>我也会觉得很难
处在你的处境下。&lt;/i>
I would also find it difficult
in your situation.
我的乳房真的很疼。
疼得要命。
My breasts are really sore.
It hurts like crazy.
- 你一开始也有这种感觉吗？
&lt;i>- 没有，亨利。别再这样了。&lt;/i>
- Did you have that in the beginning too?
- No, Henry. Stop that.
&lt;i>马德斯，请带他走。
不！&lt;/i>
Mads, please take him.
No!
&lt;i>对不起。现在很疯狂。
我会给你回电话的。嘿！&lt;/i>
I'm sorry. It's crazy right now.
I'll call you back. Hey!
他们的贝类很好吃，
你不觉得吗？
Their shellfish is delicious,
don't you think?
你小时候吃什么？
What did you eat as a child?
为什么？
Why?
我记不太清楚了。
我真的不记得奶奶了。
I just don't remember very well.
I don't really remember Grandma.
这该死的汤里肯定没有多少贝类。
There sure aren't many shellfish
in this damn soup.
我确实记得爷爷。
I do remember Grandpa.
他烟斗的味道和他低沉的声音
我以前很害怕。
The smell of his pipe and his deep voice
I used to be so scared of.
他说话很多吗？
Did he talk a lot?
- 爷爷？
- 是的。你们相处得好吗？
- Grandpa?
- Yes. Did you get along?
他最好被描述为
一个傲慢的混蛋。
He would best be described
as an arrogant asshole.
- 还有别的吗？
- 我不想谈论他。
- And otherwise?
- I don't want to talk about him.
- 早上好，哥本哈根。
- 早上好，奥斯陆。
- Good morning, Copenhagen.
- 'Morning, Oslo.
20 公里徒步和瑜伽？
20-kilometer hike and yoga?
这些床垫
对背部真的很硬。
Those mattresses
are really hard on the back.
在朝圣之路上，控制自己的阴茎对你来说很合适。
It would suit you to control your dick
on the pilgrim's route.
你垂涎的是我的女儿。
That's my daughter you're drooling over.
她站在我面前。
我先来的。
She placed herself in front of me.
I was here first.
人们在这里寻求洞察力、安慰和智慧。
People are seeking insight,
comfort and wisdom here.
你在做什么？
这家伙只顾着自己的事情。
What are you doing?
The guy was minding his own business.
而你却在基督教朝圣之路上调情并信奉东方宗教。
And you flirt and practice an Eastern
religion on a Christian pilgrimage route.
放松。我正在伸展身体。
Relax. I'm stretching.
而瑜伽不是宗教。
And yoga is not a religion.
你今天的速度不错！
也许是上帝的速度。
You have a good speed today!
God's speed, maybe.
凉鞋很完美。
非常感谢！
The sandals are perfect.
Thank you so much!
是吗，爸爸？
谢谢！
Right, Dad?
Thank you!
- 你想和我一起去吗？
- 那会……
- You want to join me?
- That would...
哦不，不，谢谢。
Oh no, no, thanks.
那么改日再见。&lt;i>Buen Camino！&lt;/i>
Some other day then. Buen Camino!
- 我们为什么不能和她一起走？
- 我来这里是为了你妈妈的遗愿。
- Why can't we walk with her?
- I'm here for your mother's last wish.
不要和那些为情所困的大脚怪擦肩而过，他们以为这一切只是为了好玩。
Not to rub shoulders with some lovesick
Bigfoot who thinks it's all just for fun.
第 4 天
DAY 4
还有 145 公里
145 kilometers to go
&lt;i>Cruz de Ferro&lt;/i>，铁十字勋章。
Cruz de Ferro, the Iron Cross.
卡米诺的最高点。
这是一个非常重要的地方。
The highest point of the Camino.
It's a very important place.
- 你可以把石头拿出来。
- 石头？
- You can take out the stone.
- The stone?
- 我发短信给你，让你带一块石头过来。
- 我以为是开玩笑。
- I texted you to bring a stone.
- I thought it was a joke.
- 开玩笑？
- 嗯，我没听懂。
- A joke?
- Well, I didn't get it.
这块石头代表着你想摆脱的负担。
The stone represents the burden
you want to free yourself from.
通过放置这块石头，
你可以放下悲伤。
By placing this stone,
you put away your sorrows.
这可能只适用于
如果你是一个信徒。
It probably only works
if you're a believer.
我不认为这是巧合
你没有石头就来了。
I don't think it's a coincidence
you came without a stone.
- 你害怕真实的感受。
- 我不明白你的文字！
- You're afraid of real feelings.
- I didn't understand your text!
让天下的水
聚集到一处。
Let the waters under the heaven
be gathered together unto one place.
让干地露出来。
And let the dry land appear.
上帝看着是好的。
And God saw that it was good.
“创造。”
"The Creation."
这就是你妈妈看到如此壮丽景色时说的话。
That's what your mother said
when she saw a stunning view like this.
你知道我最喜欢的圣经故事是什么吗？
Do you know what my favorite story
from the Bible was?
耶稣诞生的那一页。
The one where Jesus is born.
- 圣诞福音？
- 是的。
- The Christmas Gospel?
- Yes.
父母在家招待
一群客人。听起来很不错。
Mother and father at home with
a bunch of guests. Sounds very nice.
这是对新约的资产阶级解读。
That's a rather bourgeois reading
of the New Testament.
好吧，也许是。
Well, maybe it is.
我嫉妒耶稣。
I was jealous of Jesus.
想象一下，和你的父母以及动物一起住在那个马厩里。
Imagine living in that stable
with both your parents, and animals.
你在那个马厩里连两分钟都撑不住。
You wouldn't last
two minutes in that stable.
&lt;i>- 加油！&lt;/i>
- 冷静下来！
- Vamos!
- Calm down!
- 走开！
- 你在干什么？
- Go away!
- What are you doing?
&lt;i>加油。加油。&lt;/i>
Vamos. Vamos.
- 你怎么了？
- 身上有疥疮和跳蚤。
- What's wrong with you?
- It's got scabies and fleas.
如果我朝你扔石头怎么办？
What if I threw stones at you, huh?
什么？
What?
- 你不能朝任何人扔任何东西！
- 是的，我可以！
- You can't throw anything at anyone!
- Yes, I can!
你害怕
任何形式的对抗。
You're afraid of
any kind of confrontation.
- 你说什么？
- 你不喜欢挑战，Regitze。
- What did you say?
- You don't like challenges, Regitze.
你只能避开他们。
You just avoid them.
- 这是什么意思？
- 你从不坚持任何事情。
- What's that supposed to mean?
- You never stick with anything.
兽医学、网球、烹饪
以及其他任何学科。
Veterinary studies, tennis, cooking
and whatever else there was.
我没法上兽医学校。
你忘了我患有诵读困难症吗？
I couldn't handle veterinary school.
Did you forget I'm dyslexic?
或者你只是不够坚韧。
Or maybe you just aren't tenacious.
就像你忙于经营的那家高档餐饮公司一样。
Just like that fancy catering firm
you busied yourself with.
听说过新冠疫情吗？
一切都关闭了，这不是我的错。
Ever heard about Covid?
It's not my fault everything closed.
哎哟！
Ow!
当生活艰难而不公平时，
你有两个选择：
When life is hard and unfair,
you have two options:
你要么逃跑……
要么反击。
You either run away...
or you fight back.
停下来。哎哟，停下来！
Stop. Ow, stop!
- 但没有什么能伤害你，对吧？
- 停下来。你真烦人。
- But nothing can hurt, right?
- Stop. You're so annoying.
你是随波逐流，
还是坚守立场？
Do you just go along,
or will you stand your ground?
- 我们讨论重要的事情。
- 你真是……！
- We talk about the things that matter.
- You're so...!
你好，你在做什么？
Hello, what are you doing?
嘿！
Hey!
- 你好！
&lt;i>- Buen Camino！&lt;/i>
- Hello!
- Buen Camino!
来吧。我们走吧。
Come on. Let's get going.
&lt;i>嘿！你好吗？&lt;/i>
Hey! How are you doing?
真的很糟糕！
我想回家。我要走了。
Really bad!
I want to go home. I'm bailing.
&lt;i>- Gitze，你不是……&lt;/i>
- 啊？愚蠢的联系。
- Gitze, you are not...
- Huh? Stupid connection.
你好？你说什么？
Hello? What did you say?
&lt;i>在去过那座大教堂并点燃蜡烛之前不要回家。&lt;/i>
Don't come home until you've been
to that cathedral and lit that candle.
是的。
Yes.
第 6 天
DAY 6
还有 118 公里
118 kilometers to go
- 你要喝牛奶吗？
- 是。但我喜欢鲜牛奶。
- Would you like milk?
- Yes. But I like fresh milk.
&lt;i>新鲜牛奶？新鲜牛奶？&lt;/i>
Leche fresco? Fresco?
&lt;i>新鲜牛奶&lt;/i>，是的。热牛奶……
Fresco, yes. Hot milk...
不，不。新鲜牛奶……
No, no. Fresh...
这种牛奶可以永远保存。
我想要新鲜的……直接从……
This milk lasts forever.
I want fresh... straight from...
- Gitze，这是咖啡。冷静点。
- 在 cortado 的土地上还有这样的咖啡？
- Gitze, it's coffee. Calm down.
- Coffee like this in the land of cortado?
&lt;i>- Caliente。&lt;/i> 热的。可以吗？
- 可以。
- Caliente. Hot. It's okay?
- Okay.
谢谢。
Thank you.
我受不了超高温牛奶。
有余味。
I can't stand UHT milk.
It has that aftertaste.
你妈妈煮的咖啡太难喝了。
天哪，太难喝了！
Your mother made bad coffee.
Good grief, it was awful!
水温不高，咖啡豆也太少，
但我毫无怨言地喝了下去 -
Lukewarm water and too few beans,
but I drank it without complaining -
因为咖啡不重要，重要的是和谁一起喝。
because it's not about coffee.
Everything is about who you drink it with.
能和你妈妈一起喝，我很幸运。
I was lucky to drink it with your mother.
爸爸，我们能不能有半个小时不谈论妈妈？
Dad, can we have half an hour
when we don't talk about Mom?
你和爱情呢？
What about you and love?
你的生活中还没有其他人吗？
Still no one else in your life?
我生活中有很多人。
There are lots of people in my life.
我有一个非常亲密的朋友。
她的名字叫丽莎。
I have a really close friend.
Her name is Lisa.
但你没有爱你的人，
也没有你爱的人。
But you don't have someone who loves you,
and don't have someone you love.
爱需要勇气。别无他法。
你只需要敢于去做。
Love takes courage. Nothing else.
You just have to dare to do it.
敢于让自己变得脆弱和无助。
Dare to make yourself
vulnerable and defenseless.
也许是缺乏勇气？
Maybe it's the courage that's lacking?
我不想谈论我和我爸爸的爱情生活。
I don't want to talk
about my love life with my dad.
我有朋友可以做到。
I have my friends for that.
顺便说一句，朋友也是爱。
And by the way, friends are love too.
而且你不会分享很多关于你自己的事情。
And it's not like you share
a whole lot about yourself.
有时感觉就像你在讲课。
Sometimes
it feels like you're giving a lecture.
好吧，我们不必再谈论它了。
Well, we don't have to talk
any more about it.
爸爸？
Dad?
- 嗨。
- 你好。
- Hi.
- Hello.
- 他在干什么？
- 爸爸！
- What's he doing?
- Dad!
- 嘿……
- 你在干什么？
- Hey there...
- What are you doing?
- 爸爸，你在干什么？
- 他是糖尿病患者吗？
- Dad, what are you doing?
- Is he diabetic?
爸爸，看我！
Dad, look at me!
- 别……
- 醒醒！
- Don't...
- Wake up!
- 他血糖过低！
- 这里不允许暴力！
- He's hypoglycemic!
- Violence has no place here!
- 爸爸，你要去哪里？
- 听我说！
- Where are you going, Dad?
- Listen to me!
他显然是糖尿病患者。
你是他的女儿。你一定知道！
He's clearly diabetic.
You're his daughter. You must know!
你有饼干或果汁吗？
他需要糖。
Do you have a cookie or juice?
He needs sugar.
- 他不是糖尿病患者。
- 我会解决这个问题。
- He isn't diabetic.
- I'll fix this.
- 他现在需要糖！
- 等一下！
- He needs sugar, now!
- Wait up!
我们会处理好的。别担心。
We'll take care of it. Don't worry.
他现在会没事的。
He'll be fine now.
- 让他摄入糖分很重要。
- 是的。
- It's important that he gets sugar.
- Yes.
爸爸？喝点。
Dad? Drink.
没有补给品，你就不能去远足。
You can't go on a hike without supplies.
- 坐在阴凉处。
- 你还好吗？
- Sit in the shade.
- Are you all right?
爸爸，你有糖尿病吗？
Do you have diabetes, Dad?
是的。
Yes.
你不认为我应该知道吗？
And you didn't think I should know that?
这不是你炫耀的东西。
这是老年糖尿病。真的很迷人。
It's not something you flaunt.
It's old man diabetes. Really charming.
我们必须确保
你吃喝。
We have to make sure
that you eat and drink.
确保你注射胰岛素。
这不是开玩笑。
Make sure you take your insulin.
It is not a joke.
这是 2 型糖尿病，到目前为止
我不需要任何胰岛素。
It's type 2, and so far
I don't need any insulin.
我是个成年人了。我可以自己照顾饼干和果汁。
I'm a grown man. I can take care
of my own crackers and juice.
显然你不能！瑞典人做到了。
Clearly you can't! The Swedes did.
当你们是一家人时，你们会互相告诉对方这些事情。
You tell each other these things
when you're a family.
就像我想知道妈妈第一次生病时的情况一样。
Just like I would have liked to know
when Mom first got sick.
- 我们不想让你担心。
- 骨癌，3 期！
- We didn't want to worry you.
- Bone cancer, stage 3!
我有充分的理由担心。
There was every conceivable
reason for me to worry.
是的。
Yeah.
有些事情很难说。
Some things are hard to say.
嗨。
Hi.
圣胡利安修道院 -
Monasterio de San Julian de Samos -
1558 年被烧毁
后来重建。
burned down in 1558
and was later rebuilt.
对于卡米诺来说，这是一个具有巨大象征意义的地方。
It's a place of enormous symbolic value
for the Camino.
这里有哥特式、巴洛克式
和文艺复兴时期的建筑。
There's Gothic, Baroque
and Renaissance architecture.
爸爸，糖尿病！
你需要吃点东西喝点东西。
Dad, diabetes!
You need to eat and drink something.
我正在努力为你打开世界。
让这座修道院产生历史共鸣 -
I'm trying to open the world for you. To
give this monastery historical resonance -
- 你想谈谈饼干吗？
- and you want to talk about crackers?
好吧，我只是想……
Well, I'm just trying to...
我们总是为旅行做好准备，
你妈妈和我 -
We always prepared for a trip,
your mother and I -
- 了解了我们在路上会看到什么。
- learned about what we'd see on our way.
圣本笃建立了许多修道院。
最重要的是，意大利的卡西诺山 -
Saint Benedict founded many monasteries.
Most importantly, Monte Cassino in Italy -
他被埋葬在
他姐姐斯科拉斯蒂卡的墓地。
where he was buried at the same place
as his sister, Scholastica.
嘿，亲爱的。
现在不是个好时机。
Hey, sweetie.
It's not a great time right now.
- 丽莎，现在不是个好时机。
&lt;i>- 帮帮我。&lt;/i> 没有电话。
- Lisa, it's not a good time.
- Por favor. No phone.
我被僧侣训斥了。
我会给你回电话。再见。
I'm getting scolded by a monk.
I'll call you back. Bye.
- 你为什么还要接电话？
- 冷静点。我挂了，好吗？
- Why do you even pick up?
- Relax. I hung up, all right?
这是修道院！
这不是你当地的时髦咖啡馆。
This is a monastery!
It's not your local hipster café.
你需要降低声音。这是一座修道院。人们生活在沉默中。
You need to lower your voice. This is
a monastery. People live in silence.
表示尊重！
Show respect!
我们走着走着。
We're walking and walking.
&lt;i>- 然后呢？&lt;/i>
- 我的意思是...
- And?
- I mean...
我们就是合不来。
We just don't get along.
&lt;i>那荷兰人呢？&lt;/i>
And what about the Dutch guy?
我认为他不想知道
他要当爸爸了。
I don't think he wants to know
he's going to be a dad.
那么，你的水泡怎么样了？
So, how are your blisters?
- 凉鞋有帮助。
- 哦。很好。
- The sandals helped.
- Oh. Good.
朝圣是一种仪式运动，
追求距离和行为。
A pilgrimage is a ceremonial movement,
that goes for the distance, behavior.
一切都是既定的，
不只是自由发挥或四处巡游。
It's all established,
not just freestyling or cruising around.
- 模式是基础。
- 是的，这是一种仪式，一种漫长的仪式。
- The pattern is the foundation.
- Yes, it's a rite, an elongated ritual.
而且，它为朝圣者提供了宗教复兴和思想改变。
And, it offers the pilgrim
a religious renewal and change of mind.
- 成年礼。
- 其中包括分离状态。
- A rite of passage.
- And it includes the state of separation.
过渡阶段。朝圣者重复过去神话人物所教的内容。
The liminal phase. Pilgrims repeat what
mythical persons were taught in the past.
一遍又一遍地重复，
然后就会出现某种模式 -
Repetition again and again,
and then a certain pattern will appear -
在那一刻，
模式到达了更多...
and at that moment
the pattern arrives to even more...
没错。你应该在某个时候走一走
Exactly. You should walk
the Via Francigena at some point.
- It's such a beautiful pilgrimage.
- Maybe I will.
- 好的。&lt;i>Buen Camino！&lt;/i>
- 再见。
- Okay. Buen Camino!
- Bye.
- 你应该追这样的男人。
That's the kind of man you should chase.
- 我会无聊得要死。
- 无聊？
- I'd be bored to death.
- Bored?
和这么聪明的人在一起？
With someone of such intellect?
- 你看起来真漂亮。
- 我每 15 分钟就要小便一次。
- You look beautiful.
- I have to pee every 15 minutes.
- 真的吗？
- 但怀孕真好。
- Oh really?
- But being pregnant is wonderful.
- 那孩子的父亲呢？他在吗？
- 他真是个混蛋。
- And the father? Is he here?
- He's a piece of shit.
我正走着，想找到离开他的力量。
I'm walking to find the strength
to leave him.
天气不错。
Nice weather.
我不太在乎天气。
我来这里是为了纪念我已故的妻子。
I don't care so much about the weather.
I'm here to honor my late wife.
- 我第三次来这里。
- 第三次？
- I'm here for the third time.
- The third time?
第一次，我走卡米诺，因为我的丈夫在车祸中丧生。
First time, I walked the Camino because
my husband died in a car accident.
52岁。
52 years old.
我第二次走朝圣之路时
我得了乳腺癌。
Second time I walked the Camino
I had the cancer of the breast.
现在我走朝圣之路是因为我最好的朋友
去年死于白血病。
Now I walk the Camino because my best
friend died from leukemia last year.
我非常想念她。
I miss her, a lot.
但走路对我有好处。
你知道，向前看。
But it's good for me to walk.
You know, move forward.
而且我认为我已经战胜了癌症。
虽然没有承诺，但我有希望。
And I think I survived cancer.
No promises, but I have hope.
- 我需要休息一下。
- 哦，当然。
- I need a little rest.
- Oh, sure.
- 再见！
- 再见。
- Bye!
- Bye-bye.
- 再见。
- 好的，再见。
- See you.
- Yeah, bye.
你还好吗？
Are you all right?
- 你要果汁还是饼干？
- 我只需要坐一会儿。
- Do you want juice or crackers?
- I just need to sit for a bit.
- 爸爸，我觉得最好...
- 我不是小孩，好吗。
- Dad, I think it would be good to...
- I'm not a child, okay.
我只是想帮助你。
I'm just trying to help you.
- 你看起来需要这个。
- 谢谢！
- You look like you need this.
- Thanks!
- 欢迎来到 La Senda。
- 谢谢！
- Welcome to La Senda.
- Thanks!
您好，&lt;i>先生&lt;/i>。
Hello, señor.
- 这咖啡很好喝。
- 西班牙人就是这样煮咖啡的。
- This coffee is very good.
- This is how we make coffee in Spain.
不，不是。相信我。
No, it's not. Believe me.
这不是你在卡米诺路上煮咖啡的方式。
This is not how you make coffee
on the fucking Camino.
这里有宗教人士。
脏话可能会冒犯某人。
There are religious people here.
Bad words might offend someone.
哦，当然。我很抱歉！
我通常真的不...
Oh, of course. I'm sorry!
I really don't usually...
&lt;i>这个女孩的头都长在屁股上了。&lt;/i>
The girl has her head up her ass.
&lt;i>- 夫人，请原谅&lt;/i>...
- 不，不，不。那是意大利语。
- Señora, scusi for the...
- No, no, no. That's Italian.
- 对。
- 我妈妈不懂英语。
- Right.
- My mother doesn't understand English.
她看起来疯了。
She seems bonkers.
不过还是谢谢你。
But thank you.
- 妈妈，你在干什么？
- 那个疯女孩怎么了？
- Mom, what are you doing?
- What's wrong with that crazy girl?
- 你玩吗？
- 是的。可以吗？
- You play?
- Yeah. Is it okay?
哦，你想玩吗？
好啊，可以，为什么不呢？
Oh, you want to play?
Yeah, okay, why not?
好的。
Okay.
10。
One-zero.
抱歉！
Sorry!
- 第一次踏上卡米诺之路？
- 是的。
- First time on the Camino?
- Yeah.
很可能也是最后一次。
And last time, probably.
为了取悦妈妈，我和爸爸一起散步……
有点……有点复杂。
不，我不再玩了。
你赢了。我需要去厨房帮妈妈做晚饭。
Walking with my father
to please my mother, it's...
It's a bit... It's complicated.
No, no more play for me.
You win. I need to go to the kitchen
and help my mother to make dinner.
- 给我？
- 给你和其他 20 个人。
- For me?
- For you and 20 other people.
- 但我赢了！
- 是的，你赢了。
- But I win!
- Yeah, you win.
- 也许稍后再玩？
- 再见！
- Maybe play later?
- Bye!
嗨。
Hi.
乒乓球。
Table tennis.
他们煮的咖啡很好喝。
They make good coffee.
这叫见朋友。
This is called meeting friends.
疼吗？
Did it hurt?
- 疼吗？
- 今天和 Mirna 聊天。
- Did what hurt?
- Talking to Mirna today.
你可以再试一次。
You could try again.
如果你需要和某人说话，那就说吧。
If you have a need to speak
with someone, then do it.
我来这里是为了你妈妈。
I'm here for your mother.
当然，还有什么？
Sure, what else?
还有什么？
What else?
- 我不喜欢你嘲讽的语气。
- 这不是嘲讽。
- I don't like your mocking tone.
- It's not mocking.
一切始终都是
关于你和妈妈。
Everything has just always been
about you and Mom.
妈妈和你，你和妈妈。
Mom and you, you and Mom.
我不知道你在说什么。
I don't know what you're talking about.
一切始终都是关于你们两个。
It has always been about you two.
关于聪明，
关于你读过的东西——
关于信仰、
存在和学术的无休止的争论。
所以现在我们反对
文学和灵性？
它并不总是……
不能和你在一起读书并不总是那么容易。
你有自己的兴趣。
你打网球打得好。
About being smart,
about what you had read -
and endless debates about faith,
existence and academic stuff.
So now we are against
literature and spirituality?
It just hasn't always...
It wasn't always easy
not being able to read in your company.
You had your own interests.
You were good at tennis.
上帝让风吹向被剪毛的羊。
God tempers the wind to the shorn sheep.
网球没有给我赢得很多分数
在家里，现在呢？
Tennis didn't win me a lot of points
back home, now did it?
一家人
不是一场比赛，吉茨。
Being a family
is not a competition, Gitze.
我们的餐桌上可以容纳各种各样的人。
There was room for all types of people
at our dinner table.
你从不来看我的比赛。
You never came to my matches.
妈妈总是要写布道文，
或者要召集悲伤支持小组。
Mom always had a sermon to write,
or a grief support group to gather.
你总是要批改作业。
你不知道我是否擅长。
You always had papers to grade.
You had no idea if I was any good.
- 运动对我来说毫无意义。
- 父母不是为了这项运动而来的。
- Sports doesn't mean anything to me.
- The parents didn't come for the sport.
他们是为了孩子而来的。
They came for their children.
如果你想抱怨你的童年，那就找个地方坐吧。
If you want to whine about your
childhood, find somewhere else to sit.
你好。
Hello.
酒精和 2 型糖尿病？
可以吗？
Alcohol and type 2 diabetes?
Is that allowed?
放松。我来是为了和平。
Relax. I come in peace.
- 一杯可乐，&lt;i>谢谢。
- 给她一杯啤酒。
- A Coke, por favor.
- Una cervesa for her.
也许你应该喝醉？
Maybe you should get drunk?
别想那么多了，
别在意别人怎么想。
Get out of your head,
not care what everyone else thinks.
我只想要一杯可乐，可以吗？
I just want a Coke, okay?
你的母亲……
我们有时一起喝得酩酊大醉。
Your mother...
We got very drunk together sometimes.
我们聊天，做爱。
We talked, we made love.
爸爸，请不要这样。我明白了。
Dad, please don't. I get it.
我明白
你很悲伤，而且……
I understand
that you're grieving and that...
不，我受尽折磨，该死的，
从内心深处！
No, I'm in torment, goddammit,
to my very core!
我失去了我生命中的见证人，我的灵魂伴侣。
I've lost my life witness, my soulmate.
没有爱，你什么都不是，当你孤身一人时，什么都不是。
You're nothing without love,
nothing when you're alone.
你仍然很了不起
尽管你孤身一人。
You're still something
although you're alone.
如果没有人听到你，如果没有人看到你，你是什么？
What are you if no one hears you,
if no one sees you?
你是你自己，
这仍然很了不起。
You're yourself,
and that's still something.
- 我一个人过得很好。
- 哦，拜托！
- I'm doing fine on my own.
- Oh, come on!
- 那是什么意思？
- 你不开心。任何人都看得出来。
- What is that supposed to mean?
- You're not happy. Anyone can see that.
- 你什么都不懂。
- 你没有爱，亲爱的。
- You don't know shit.
- You have no love, honey.
“爱让一切都变得甜蜜。”
"Everything is sweetened by love."
我还是不会谈论
我和我爸爸的爱情生活。
I'm still not talking
about my love life with my dad.
没什么好说的，
所以这真的不重要。
There's not much to talk about,
so it doesn't really matter.
好吧，现在我们到了这里，
我们只是两次什么都没有？
Okay, so now we're here,
and we're just two times nothing?
什么都没有，是吗？
Nothing at all, is that it?
- 你妈妈和我在一起。
- 我知道她在。
- Your mother is with me.
- I know she is.
你把她放在心里，
但我也在这里。
And you carry her in your heart,
but I'm here too.
那是她吗……？
Is that her...?
那是她的骨灰吗？
Is that her ashes?
在你的腰包里吗？
In your fanny pack?
你告诉我妈妈的骨灰盒
被放在公墓里了。
You told me Mom's urn
was placed in the common grave.
- 你骗我？
- 不，我只是放不下。
- You lied to me?
- No, I just couldn't let go.
想到伊丽莎白的骨灰
洒在黑暗中……
这不可能是真的！
我不知道该说什么。
- 你不要这么做！
- 你不懂悲伤！
你不懂真正的悲伤，真正的渴望。
这就像一把刺进心脏的刀。
The thought of Elisabeth's ashes
down in the dark...
This can't be real!
I don't know what to say.
- You just don't do that!
- You don't know grief!
You don't know real grief, real longing.
It's a knife to the heart.
谁会带着死去的妻子去西班牙的酒吧
并对他们的女儿撒谎？
Who takes their dead wife to a bar
in Spain and lies to their daughter?
她梦见了卡米诺，
她梦见了那座大教堂——
She dreamed of the Camino,
she dreamed of that cathedral -
我打算确保
她能体验到这一切。
and I intend to make sure
she experiences it.
她再也不会做梦了！
她什么都体验不到！
She doesn't dream anymore!
She can't experience anything!
她死了！记住这一点！
She is dead! Get it into your head!
别管我！
Leave me alone!
- 不，该死的！伊丽莎白！
- 不要呼吸！不要呼吸！
- No, goddammit! Elisabeth!
- Don't breathe! Don't breathe!
求求你，谁都别呼吸！这是我妈妈！
Nobody breathe, please! It's my mother!
- 让我来帮你。
- 我自己可以！
- Let me help you.
- I can do it myself!
她身上有个洞。
把袋子关紧。
There's a hole in her.
Keep the bag closed.
- 我要回家了。
- 不，Gitze，停下来！
- I'm going home.
- No, Gitze, stop!
我不是我自己，你知道吗？
我感觉很糟糕，好吗？
I'm not myself, you know?
I feel like shit, all right?
你打我了！
You hit me!
对不起。我喝醉了。
喝酒对我真的很不好。
I'm sorry. I'm totally drunk.
Drinking is really bad for me.
- 我还是要回家。
- 不，Gitze。操。该死的。停下来！
- I'm still going home.
- No, Gitze. Fuck. Goddammit. Stop!
别碰我。
Don't touch me.
你得打我！这样我们就扯平了。
You have to hit me! Then we're even.
- 我不想！
- 是的！别这么卑鄙。
- I don't want to!
- Yes! Don't be such a doormat.
- 你刚才叫我什么？
- 来吧，卑鄙的人！
- What did you just call me?
- Come on, doormat!
你知道吗，爸爸？我们完了。
You know what, Dad? We're done.
我们根本就不适合彼此。
We're just no good for each other.
我们互相误解，
我们互相伤害……
We misunderstand each other,
we hurt each other...
好吧，你伤害了我，
所以我现在要去孔波斯特拉了——
Well, you're hurting me,
so now I'm going on to Compostela -
然后我会飞回家。
但你可以走你的朝圣之路。
and then I'll fly home.
But you can walk your Camino.
Gitze...
结束了！你不给我打电话，
我也不给你打电话。
It's over! You don't call me,
and I don't call you.
好吧，&lt;i>Buen Camino。&lt;/i>
Well, Buen Camino.
嘿...
Hey...
有一件事
我认为你应该知道。
There's one thing
I thought you should know.
我怀孕了。
I'm pregnant.
什么？
What?
我真的很期待……
And I'm really looking forward...
我相信
我会成为一个好妈妈。
And I do believe
I'll be a pretty good mother.
- 等到明天再去怎么样？
- 不用了，谢谢！
- How about wait and go tomorrow?
- No, thank you!
&lt;i>我是 Lisa。请留言。&lt;/i>
It's Lisa. Please leave a message.
嘿，是我。我离开了他。
我不想再和他在一起了。
Hey, it's me. I left him.
I don't want to be with him anymore.
他他妈的打我了！
他真是个傲慢的混蛋。
He fucking hit me!
He's such an arrogant asshole.
我只想回家。
I just want to go home.
&lt;i>你好，我是 Martjin。
你好？这是谁？&lt;/i>
Hello, this is Martjin.
Hello? Who is this?
第 9 天
DAY 9
还有 36 公里
36 kilometers to go
&lt;i>一路平安，&lt;/i>哥本哈根！
Buen Camino, Copenhagen!
今天不太爱说话？
Not very talkative today?
我们可以一起走，
一起保持沉默？
We could walk together,
be silent together?
- 你说什么？
- 我们可以一起走，保持沉默。
- What did you say?
- We can walk and be silent together.
- 你真的在勾引我吗？
- 对不起？
- You're seriously hitting on me?
- Excuse me?
你在卡米诺勾引我！
You are hitting on me on the Camino!
我只是想我们可以一起走，
现在你和你爸爸都不在了……
I just thought we might walk together,
now that you and your dad aren't...
这是自中世纪以来朝圣者们徒步的地方！
This is a place where pilgrims
have hiked since the Middle Ages!
这不是搭讪女士们的地方
让她们在睡袋里保持温暖。
It's not a place to pick up ladies
to stay warm in your sleeping bag.
我怀孕了。
你听到了吗，嗯？
I'm pregnant.
Did you hear that, huh?
是的，我怀孕了！
Yes, I'm pregnant!
我可不是什么花瓶！
I'm not just some bimbo!
挪威，请尊重点！
Show some respect, Norway!
什么？
What?
- 你好。
- 你好，我要去孔波斯特拉。
- Hello.
- Hi, I need to go to Compostela.
- 孔波斯特拉。当然。
- 现在在出租车上。
- Compostela. Of course.
- In a taxi, right now.
是的，但我们有一个问题。
我们这里没有出租车。
Yes, but we have a problem.
We have no taxis here.
但也许我可以为你从孔波斯特拉叫一辆出租车。
But maybe I can call one taxi
from Compostela for you.
- 是的，那太好了。
- 三个小时，两个小时。我不知道。
- Yes, that would be great.
- Three hours, two hours. I don't know.
- 尽快。
- 我需要查找电话号码。
- As quick as possible.
- I need to look for the phone number.
Gitze，我一直在找你。
Gitze, I've been looking
all over for you.
- 哦，嗨！
- 你好。
- Oh, hi!
- Hello.
你在这里做什么？
What are you doing here?
你父亲，
他今天早上表现得很奇怪。
Your father,
he acted quite strange this morning.
然后他晕倒了，摔倒了，撞到了头。
也许他得了脑震荡。
Then he fainted, fell and hit his head.
Maybe he had a concussion.
医生看过他了。他需要休息。
The doctor saw him. He needs rest.
- 是吗？
- 我想你应该知道。
- Yeah?
- I thought you should know.
我不知道。也许你想回去
看看你的父亲？
I don't know. Maybe you want to go back
and see your father?
不，我不想回去。
No, I don't want to go back.
我就是做不到。
I just can't.
听着。
我父亲不是一个很善良的人。
Listen.
My father wasn't a very kind man.
我们之间有过争吵，他和我。
We had our fights, him and me.
政治、伦理、音乐、社会、
难民，实际上一切都有争吵。
Politics, ethics, music, society,
refugees, everything really.
现在他走了，我非常想念他。
Now he's gone, and I miss him so much.
每天。
Every day.
你们在一起的所有故事。
我可以说：
All the stories you have together.
I could say:
“还记得阿尔梅里亚那只有趣的狗吗？”
我们会笑 -
"Remember the funny dog in Almeria?"
and we would laugh -
因为我们曾经在阿尔梅里亚见过一只有趣的狗。
because we once saw
a funny dog in Almeria.
但现在我……
But now I...
那只是他和我。
That was only for him and me.
现在我只能孤零零地想着那只狗的形象。
Now I'm stuck with the image
of that dog, all alone.
我现在甚至想不起和父亲发生过的任何有趣的故事。
I can't even remember one single
funny story with my father right now.
但我想你会的。
But I think you will.
- 谢谢。
&lt;i>- Claro。&lt;/i>
- Thank you.
- Claro.
嗨，爸爸。
Hi, Dad.
- 嗨！
- 嗨。
- Hi!
- Hi.
- 所以你真的怀孕了？
- 是的。
- So you're really pregnant?
- Yes.
太棒了！
That's fantastic!
嗯，当然。
Well, sure.
但还是很新。
But it's still very new.
我才十周。所以，是的。
I'm only at ten weeks. So, yeah.
所以，还有一段路要走。
So, there's still some way to go.
那么，孩子的父亲是谁？
So, who's the father?
没有父亲。
There is no father.
- 总是有父亲的。
- 在这种情况下，不是这样的。
- There's always a father.
- Not really in this case, no.
所以你不知道是谁让你怀孕的？
So you don't know who got you pregnant?
是的，我知道我是怎么怀孕的，
但没有男朋友。
Yes, I know how I got pregnant,
but there's no boyfriend.
那只是一个荷兰人 -
It was just some Dutch guy -
- 我和他见过一面。
- who I saw very briefly.
他对此一无所知。
He doesn't know any of this.
- 你能找到他吗？
- 我想不可能。
- You could find him?
- I don't think so.
他有妻子和两个孩子。
我不能那么做。
He has a wife and two children.
I can't do that.
但你不可能自己生孩子。
But you can't have a child by yourself.
为什么不呢？
Why not?
因为那太自私了
而且非常可悲。
Because that's very selfish
and incredibly sad.
你有没有想过
生孩子的责任有多大？
Have you even considered how great
a responsibility having a child is?
是真的吗？你别说。
我当然知道！
It is, really? You don't say.
Of course I know that!
- 你还是可以摆脱它的。
- 你说什么？
- You can still get rid of it.
- What did you say?
如果我没记错的话
限制是 12 周。
If I remember correctly
the limit is 12 weeks.
嘿！你不应该对我和我的怀孕有任何意见 -
Hey! You're not supposed to have
an opinion about me and my pregnancy -
绝对不应该对堕胎有任何意见！
and definitely not
about having an abortion!
我们可以谈论一些事情。
我有权说出我的想法。
We can talk about things.
It's my right to say what I think.
你需要保持安静并闭上眼睛
因为你有脑震荡。
You need to be quiet and close your eyes
because you have a concussion.
这……这是我的决定。
This... this is my decision.
你不需要跟我和我的孩子有任何关系。
You don't need to have anything
to do with me and my child.
一点也不。
Not at all.
我永远不想再和你讨论这件事了 -
And I never ever
want to discuss this with you -
- 永远都不想。
- ever again.
嗨！你终于接电话了。
Hi! Finally you pick up.
&lt;i>- 我们在同一个时区！&lt;/i>
- 但我真的需要和你谈谈。
- We're in the same time zone!
- But I really need to speak with you.
&lt;i>当西班牙是夜晚时，
丹麦也是夜晚。&lt;/i>
When it's night in Spain,
it's night in Denmark too.
抱歉。
Sorry.
&lt;i>这得等到明天了。
时间是...&lt;/i>
This has to wait until tomorrow.
The time is...
好的，再见。
Okay, bye.
- 嗨。
- Hi.
- 小心。那个疯狂的女孩又回来了。
- Watch out. The crazy girl is back.
- 你妈妈说什么？
- 一句古老的西班牙问候语。
- What does your mother say?
- An old Spanish greeting.
哦，好的。
Oh, okay.
&lt;i>谢谢！&lt;/i> &lt;i>祝您好运&lt;/i>
Gracias! And buenos días.
我会再为您制作一杯 cortado。
I will make you another cortado.
不，我只是……
No, I just...
- 关于烹饪。
- 不，不，不……
- About the cooking.
- No, no, no...
这是加利西亚，
我们有西班牙最好的厨房。
This is Galicia,
and we have the finest kitchen in Spain.
- 当然。
- 我妈妈是个很棒的厨师。
- Of course.
- My mother was a great cook.
- 但她现在老了，好吗？
有点痴呆。
But she's old now, okay?
Has a bit of dementia.
- 我们尽我们所能。
- 当然！
- We do the best we can.
- Of course!
- 我只是想问你
我是否可以在厨房帮忙？
I just wanted to ask you
if I could help out in the kitchen?
- 你呢？
- 是的，我会做饭。
- You?
- Yes, I can cook.
我真的，真的需要做点什么。
And I really,
really need something to do.
她问，
她能不能帮忙做晚饭。
She asks,
if she can help cooking dinner.
当然。吃淘气女孩做的晚餐真是一种享受。
Of course. It's a pleasure
eating dinner made by naughty girls.
&lt;i>是吗？&lt;/i>
Sí?
&lt;i>- 是，是。&lt;/i>
- 意思是“是”？
- Sí, sí.
- Means "yes"?
&lt;i>谢谢，夫人！&lt;/i>
Gracias, señora!
让我看看……
Let me see...
我可以用&lt;i>火腿&lt;/i>做这些洋蓟吗？
I could make these artichokes
with the jamón?
&lt;i>Alcachofas con Jamón.&lt;/i>
Alcachofas con Jamón.
- 非常好。
- 很好。
- It's very good.
- It's fine.
嗨。
Hi.
给你。吃吧。
Here you go. Eat.
不，我不想谈论它。
And no, I don't want to talk about it.
吃你的食物。
Eat your food.
你妈妈似乎
她有一个非常……大个性。
Your mother seems like
she has a very... big personality.
你别说！
You don't say!
事实上，今天是六周前
我母亲去世的日子。
It's actually six weeks ago today
that my mother died.
他们消失的时候很奇怪。
It's strange when they disappear.
他们一直在那里，
突然间他们就不见了。
They were always there,
and suddenly they're not.
我其实开始有点想念她了。
I'm actually starting to miss her
a little bit.
是的。
Yeah.
我觉得自己是个非常冷漠的人 -
I felt like a really cold person -
- 不想念她。
- not missing her.
冷漠？你呢？
Cold? You?
不，我不这么认为。
No, I don't think so.
蒂托！
Tito!
问女孩
是否想做饭。
Ask the girl
if she wants to prepare the food.
我妈妈问你能否帮我们做晚饭？
My mother asks if you would be kind
and help us with dinner?
是的，我很乐意！
Yeah, I would love to!
- 脑震荡怎么样了？
- 头痛消失了。
- How's the concussion?
- The headache is gone.
- 我饿极了。
- 太好了。那就坐吧。
- And I'm starving.
- Great. Then take a seat.
- 我该接受吗？
- 是的。
- Should I take that?
- Yeah.
- 食物很好吃。
- 不客气。
- The food was nice.
- You're welcome.
我真不敢相信你……
I can't believe that you...
我真不敢相信……
I can't believe...
爸爸，快点。求你停下来。
Dad, come on. Please stop.
你能不能别那么夸张？
Can you please turn down the drama?
爸爸，我会自己想办法的。
Dad, I'll figure this out on my own.
行吗？
All right?
你知道，很多女性都是单身母亲。
Lots of women manage
as single mothers, you know.
你知道你的母亲梦想有个孙子吗？
Did you know that your mother
dreamt of having a grandchild?
想象一下，如果她能体验成为祖母的感觉。
Imagine if she could have experienced
becoming a grandmother.
她对我们的关系感到很痛苦，
你和我相处得并不融洽 -
She was tormented by our relationship,
that you and I didn't get along -
而且事情已经到了
我们不再见面的地步。
and that it had gotten to the point
where we stopped seeing each other.
- 你还记得吗？
- 还记得什么？
- Do you even remember?
- Remember what?
你不记得
我们为什么一点儿也没见过面吗？
You don't remember
why we haven't seen each other at all?
你还记得你叫我什么吗？
Do you remember what you called me?
嗯……
Well...
你叫我——
You called me -
——你一生中最失望的人。
- the disappointment of your life.
——是的。
- Yeah.
——我喝多了。
- 是的，你可能已经这样做了。
- I had a little too much to drink.
- Yeah, you probably had.
你这么说并没有伤害到我。
It didn't hurt so much that you said it.
更重要的是 -
It was more the fact -
- 你真的是这个意思。
- that you really meant it.
这就是你对我的感觉。
That's how you feel about me.
我认为你太重视它了。
I think you gave it too much importance.
这可能吗？
Is that even possible?
Can you give it too much importance?
But, Gitze, look at you now.
You nourish people's bodies.
Sure, but...
- 你妈妈滋养了人们的灵魂。
- 我现在真的不需要你的赞美。
- Your mom nourished people's souls.
- I really don't need your praise now.
但是，吉泽……
But, Gitze...
我曾经确信自己是一个伟大的思想家。
I once had myself convinced
that I was a great thinker.
我确信我会写出改变世界的重要书籍。
I was sure I was going to write
important books that changed the world.
但我成为了一名高中老师。
你的祖父不尊重这一点。
But I became a high school teacher.
Your grandfather didn't respect that.
我们每次在一起时，他都会嘲笑我。
He mocked me
every time we were together.
并且让我知道
我是他最失望的人。
And made sure I knew that I was
his biggest disappointment.
我觉得自己是个巨大的失败者。
I felt like a huge failure.
这就是我的结局。
That's how I've ended up.
一个可以炫耀
并引用克尔凯郭尔的人。
Someone who can show off
and cite Kierkegaard.
好吧，这还是有点意义的。
Well, that's still something.
无论如何，现在做任何事情都太晚了。
At any rate, it's too late
to do anything about it now.
现在我终于把所有的失望都发泄在你身上了。
And now I've ended up throwing
all my disappointment at you.
- 不行。
- That's not okay.
- No.
而且我也喝太多了。
And I also drink too much.
- 我搞过其他女人。
- 我不需要知道。
- I screwed other women.
- I don't need to know.
- 你妈妈和海涅也搞过。
- 不，不，不！
- Your mother and Heine screwed too.
- No, no, no!
是的。
Yeah.
有悲伤和失落。
There are sorrows and losses.
还有我们对彼此所做的事情的羞耻和内疚。
And there's the shame and guilt
about what we did to each other.
上帝可能会治愈羞耻和内疚。
这就是你母亲会说的话。
Shame and guilt God may heal.
That's what your mother would claim.
但悲伤和失落呢？
But sorrow and loss?
现在我一个人承受着这一切。
I'm alone with that now.
嗨。
Hi.
- 谢谢你的音乐！
- 晚餐真棒。
- Thank you for the music!
- Great dinner.
- 晚餐。
- 哦，是的。
- Dinner.
- Oh, yes.
&lt;i>太棒了！真棒。&lt;/i>
Bellissima! Buena.
每个人都能感受到你烹饪的快乐和热情。
Everybody can taste your joy
and passion for cooking.
我不知道。
只是一些油和洋葱 -
I don't know.
It was just some oil and onions -
- 你漂亮的蔬菜。
- your beautiful vegetables.
是吗？
Yes?
我怀孕了。
I'm pregnant.
&lt;i>Embarazada。&lt;/i>
你怀孕了吗？
Embarazada.
You're with child?
是的。没有父亲。
没有爸爸，但我怀了一个孩子。
Yes. There's no father.
There's no dad, but I'm with a baby.
- 一个小的。
- 恭喜！
- A small one.
- Congratulations!
谢谢。是的，我……
Thank you. Yeah, I'm...
我很高兴。
I'm happy.
我想。
I think.
我有……我妈妈。
我得帮她上床睡觉……
I have... my mother.
I have to help her to bed...
否则，
她会忘记上床睡觉……
Otherwise,
she forgets to go to bed and...
我得在睡觉前摆好桌子准备早餐。
I have to lay the table for breakfast
and prepare before I go to bed.
一个。
一个就好了。
One.
It would be great with a one.
两个。
Two.
我累了。
I'm tired.
我们回家吧。
也许你的追求者可以开车送我们？
Let's go home.
Maybe your suitor could drive us?
他不是我的追求者。
He's not my suitor.
那我们为妈妈点的大教堂和蜡烛呢？
What about the cathedral
and candle we were lighting for Mom?
去机场之前我们还有时间。
We have time
before going to the airport.
第 11 天
DAY 11
还剩 5 公里
5 kilometers to go
- 大教堂很漂亮，不是吗？
- 是的，很漂亮。
- The cathedral is beautiful, no?
- Yeah, it's beautiful.
太棒了！
It's amazing!
你来吗？
Are you coming?
实际上，我不来了。
Actually, I'm not.
- 怎么了？
- 我再也看不到它了。
- What's wrong?
- I just don't see it anymore.
看到了什么？
See what?
我宁愿只是坐着
喝一杯咖啡。
I'd rather just sit
and drink a cup of coffee.
这就是你妈妈和我
一直做的事。我们只是坐着。
That's what your mother and I
always did. We would just sit.
喝咖啡，看着人们
和生活从我们身边经过。
Drink coffee and look at people
and life as it passed us by.
- 我更愿意这样做。
- 我想带妈妈去。
- I'd much rather do that.
- I want to bring Mom.
好的。
Okay.
我的母亲。
My mother.
- 你好！
- 哦，你好！
- Hello!
- Oh, hello!
你去过大教堂吗？
You've been inside the cathedral yet?
不，我一生中见过很多教堂和大教堂。
No, I've seen lots of churches
and cathedrals in my time.
你是信徒还是建筑师？
You're a believer or an architect?
谢谢！
Thanks!
嗯，我妻子是个信徒。
她是个牧师。
Well, my wife was a believer.
She was a priest.
或者牧师！
Or a minister!
你呢？
And you?
现在，我喝咖啡。
Right now, I'm a coffee drinker.
你知道，萨格勒布有一座非常漂亮的大教堂。
We have a very beautiful cathedral
in Zagreb, you know.
我没听说过。
I haven't heard about it.
是的。如果你来萨格勒布——
Yeah. If you ever come to Zagreb -
你应该给我打电话，
我会带你去的。
you should give me a call,
and I'll show it to you.
- 这就是我们所做的，不是吗？
- 我们做什么？
- That's what we do, isn't it?
- What's what we do?
我们喝咖啡。我们结识新朋友。
We drink coffee. We meet new people.
我们继续前行。我们继续前进。
We walk on. We move on.
好吧...再见！
Well... bye!
再见。
Bye-bye.
为一个活着的人点蜡烛有意义吗？
Does it make sense to light a candle
for a living person?
你可以为失去的人点蜡烛 -
You can light a candle
for someone you have lost -
- 或者为一个你希望好的人点蜡烛 -
- or for someone you wish well -
- 为一个新生儿，为每个人。
- for a newborn child, for everybody.
这是给我的孩子的。
这是给我父亲的。
This is for my baby.
This is for my father.
你在哪里？
And where are you?
我不知道。
I don't know.
- 谢谢。
- 谢谢你照顾我。
- Thank you.
- Thank you for taking care of me.
随时都可以，&lt;i>爸爸！&lt;/i>
Any time, Papá!
所以... 是的。
So... yeah.
对我来说，今年夏天能遇见你是件非常高兴的事。
For me, it was this summer's pleasure
to meet you.
真的。
Really.
对我来说也是。
For me too.
是的。好吧，再见！
Yeah. Well, goodbye!
你在做什么？
你不能就这样让他离开！
What are you doing?
You can't just let him leave!
我告诉他我怀孕了。
这会让大多数男人失去兴趣。
I told him I'm pregnant.
It's a turn-off for most men.
不，Gitze！你还只是个单身母亲
而且才刚刚开始。
No, Gitze! You're just a single mother
at a very early stage.
如果你让他离开，那么你永远不知道会发生什么。
If you let him leave, then you'll
never know what this could be.
听着，Gitze，现在就是现在。
突然间就太晚了。
Listen, Gitze, now is now.
And suddenly it's too late.
你还好吗？
Are you okay?
- 别看！
- 对。
- Don't look!
- Right.
我……是因为……
I... It's because...
我想再见到你。是的。
I'd like to see you again. Yeah.
我想……更深入地了解你。
I'd like to... get to know you
a bit better.
也许回来，你知道……
Maybe come back and, you know...
做点吃的……
Make some food and...
是的，看看我们会发生什么。
Yeah, see what happens with us.
- 我知道。怀孕了。关掉。
- 不，不是那样。
- I know. Pregnant. Turn off.
- No, it's not that.
我生命中不能有女人。
I cannot have a woman in my life.
不是任何女人。
Not any woman.
哦，你喜欢男人，或者……
Oh, you like men, or...
不，我已经承诺
进入萨摩斯修道院 -
No, I've made a commitment
to enter the Monastery of Samos -
- 八月一日。
- on the 1st of August.
什么？为什么？
What? Why?
- 因为我相信上帝。
- 是的。
- Because I believe in God.
- Yeah.
- 萨摩斯修道院是最大的。
- 我知道。我去过那里。
- The Monastery of Samos is the biggest.
- I know. I was there.
如果有帮助的话，当我遇到你时，我真的不得不再次问自己。
If it helps, I really had to question
myself again when I met you.
- 真的。
- 这有点帮助。
- Really.
- That helps, a little.
我很抱歉，也为我自己。
I'm so sorry, also for myself.
你去做你必须做的事。
You go do what you have to do.
如果你和上帝分手了
那么请给我打电话。
And if you and God ever break up
at some point, then call me.
你将是我第一个打电话的人。
而我妈妈将是第二个。
You will be the first I call.
And my mother will be number two.
好吧，但我是认真的。
Okay, but I'm serious.
我也是。
I am too.
好的。
Okay.
谢谢！
Thank you!
为什么要当和尚？真是个白痴，
他本可以拥有像你这样的人。
Why be a monk? What an idiot,
when he could have had someone like you.
这是夸奖吗？
Was that a compliment?
如果你能为 100 个人做饭 -
If you can cook for 100 people -
- 你肯定能照顾好一个孩子。
- you can surely handle a single child.
而且父亲那边没有祖父母。
And there are no grandparents
on the father's side.
母亲那边也没有祖母。
And no grandmother on the mother's.
但肯定有爷爷。
But there sure as hell is a grandpa.
或者某种爷爷，如果你想要的话。
Or a kind of grandpa, if you want it.
我哭的时候别看我。
我看起来像一只小兔子。
Don't look at me when I cry.
I look like a little rabbit.
- 这还不算太糟？
- 味道糟透了！
- This isn't too bad?
- It tastes awful!
- 这是一次美丽的朝圣之旅。
- 也许我会的。